The Peacemongers

by POUL ANDERSON

We are now, we tell ourselves, living in peace—which means that throughout the world not very many people are being killed in not very many wars, and that in this country the Armed Forces stand at less than 700% of their strength before Pearl Harbor and not much more than two-thirds of the national budget is connected with "defense.” But have you ever stopped to think, as Air. Anderson has, of the results if insidious and subversive forces were really to precipitate an active state of peace?

At night, from above, the enormous dinginess of Chicago became a carelessly sprawled dragon’s hoard, a million winking jewels and clotted gold fountains. Among them flashed the new Civic Auditorium, turned into one great neon billboard. Royce squinted through the copter window, trying to make it out.

There was the usual heroic soldier with the usual look of muscular determination, his bayonet staving off a giant slug-like monster with fangs while a leggy, busty blonde holding a goldenhaired tot cheered him on. The slug’s face was recognizably—just short of libel—patterned on Sam Royce. The caption read:

REMEMBER SAMOA!

HELP SAVE YOUR COUNTRY

AND LOVED ONES

LIBERAL RALLY TONITE

"Hell of a time for us to meet," grumbled Buechley. “Chicago’ll be crawling with Liberals, won’t it? If they learn about this confab—“

"Oh, dear,” said little Wald. His unworldly eyes fluttered around thick contact lenses. “Should we?” Royce grinned without much humor. “The Tower was built defensible,” he replied. "But I don’t think even Larson could have found out we’re meeting.”

“What happened at Samoa, anyway?” asked Buechley. He had only been back on Earth for a couple of days, and Royce had had him under wraps the whole time. “Looks like a new national slogan.”

"It is,” said Royce, “That’s where the entire Japanese fleet surrendered to us last year, with no warning whatsoever.”

Buechley whistled. He was not a scrupulous man, but treachery on such a majestic scale could appall anyone. “I suppose it produced a crisis?” he said inanely.

"Lord, yes,” answered Roycc. “If CINCOPAC hadn’t been able to lure the Russian navy out and engage ’em . . . We lost half our fleet there, brilliant operation, Admiral Hark ness got a medal out of it. But for a while the stock market nosedived, which gave the Liberal Party a big shot in the arm. If we can’t do something about it, the Liberals are going to sweep this election. Won’t be a dozen Reactionary scats left in Congress.”

His face was bleak as he maneuvered the copter toward the Wilson Tower, and he said no more until it was down on the roof. Dim light shone off the guns of his private guard, where they waited above the city. He led the way to an elevator.

Wald licked his lips. “I wonder,” he mumbled. “I really do wonder, Mr. Royce . . . Why, if this scheme of yours is ever exposed—”

“Shut up! I'm paying you to take risks.”

"And to sell my scientific soul,” whispered Wald.

Buechley gave him a hard look. The astronomer shrank away from the big spaceman.

Royce ignored them. He glanced at his watch. The rally would already have begun. Larson, the Liberal candidate for President, would start his address any minute. The man was an efficient demagogue. By the time he had finished, the Reactionary name in Chicago would be rich dark mud. And all over the nation, folk would be nodding agreement at their television screens.

“Old isolationists never die,” murmured Royce. “They just rave away.”

The elevator let the three of them out into a noiselessly plush corridor paneled with golden oak. Royce walked quickly toward the room at the end. The guards there presented arms. "Everybody’s arrived, sir,”

“Good,” said Roycc. “Now keep everybody else out of here. And any of you who so much as him at this get-together, any time in the future, will be boiled with white wine for my dinner.”

He adjusted his diamond stickpin, opened the soundproof door, and walked in to meet the men who ruled the Earth.

Or their representatives, at least. And the rule was a precarious one. Royce’s Reactionary Party could well be turned out at the coming election; Castro might wake up any morning to find counter-revolution snarling through the streets of Buenos Aires; the College of Commissars might choose a Vozhd leaning toward Orthodox Marxism when feeble old Grigorovitch died. . . . They were grim men, though well-dressed, the dozen who rose for him.

He closed the door and locked it. There were comfortable chairs around a long mahogany table, drinks and snacks on the sideboard, a full-wall transparency flickering with the faerie spectacle of Chicago after dark. But you didn’t notice the furnishings; the room was too full of tension.

Royce bowed slightly. “Good evening,” he said. “I'm sorry to be late. Had to pick these gentlemen up at the hideaway, and make damn sure none of us were seen. May I present Captain Buechley of the Corporation space service; Dr. Wald, distinguished astrophysicist from Clement Observatory.”

Lord Vallandringham, Ambassador of Great Britain, adjusted his monocle. “D’je’do,” he clipped. “I take it they are part of this mysterious plan of yours?”

Royce nodded and went to the head of the table. Wald sat shyly down at the end. Buechley helped himself at the sideboard and leaned against the wall, face impassive.

“You realize I wouldn't have called this meeting, with all the trouble of secrecy involved, if there weren’t a hell of a good reason,” began Royce. “The fact is—and we’d better face it—if our, uh, conspiracy doesn’t succeed soon, it will never succeed at all. We need a new approach, and fast.”

“Nonsense,” said the Russian, Dmitrov, brusquely. He was clad in the full canonicals of an archimandrite in the Reformed Communist Party. “Historical necessity is with us. We can’t lose.”

Royce took out a cigar and bit the end off. “Well,” he replied mildly, “perhaps the Forty-One Articles do say world peace is inevitable, but they don’t say when it will come, do they? I’d kind of like it to be in my lifetime.”

Vallandringham cleared his throat. There was a torment behind the schooled manner; he spoke for his country and his country faced ruin. “Britain is already trying,” he said harshly, “If you Americans would only help! You have the greatest consumptive capacity in the world. We don’t ask you to enter the peace with us. All we say is, ‘We have the tools, you finish the job.’ ”

“I sympathize,” answered Castro. “I would assist if I could. But it is impossible. Brazil may surrender to us any day, and then where are we?”

Oliveira, from Rio, flushed darkly. “Don’t blame us,” he snapped. “Do you think we wanted our whole Third Army forced into a pocket and surrounded? Your General Mendoza had every opportunity to by-pass us—”

“Please!” Royce smiled, rather bleakly. “International conspirators have no business getting patriotic.” He jerked a thumb at the window.

“Down there the Liberals are holding a mass meeting, nationally televised. Down there is the enemy. Perhaps you’d like to see him?”

He leaned over and turned on the TV. As he struck his cigar alight, Larson’s face leaped out of the screen, flamboyant and angry. The voice roared at them:

“—let me only recapitulate. Let me remind you of what you suffered in the last World Peace. A five-year peace, do you remember? Five years of unemployment, of bread lines, of unions decaying and the great corporations growing fat! Five years of profits for the few and misery for the many!

“They called that Second World Peace a ‘breathing spell.’ They called it a ‘tooling-up period.’ They called it ‘the peace to end peace.’ And they lied! Even now, my friends, even now the Reactionaries are engineering another peace. Even now, as armistice after armistice slinks into being, as peace treaty after peace treaty is signed , . , even now, the specter of a world without war is rising before us!

“Why, you ask, do the Reactionaries want peace? Why would any sane man want peace?

“The answer, ladies and gentlemen of America, working men of America, mothers of America, soldiers, sailors, airmen, spacemen of America—the answer is simple. Big Business wants peace for profit! Yes, for profit!

“True, when production outruns consumption, as it always docs in peacetime, there is mass unemployment. True, our gallant servicemen are out of work. True, their fathers and brothers walk the streets past empty munitions plants. But there are always some who have work. Especially the technicians in the automated factories, on the automated farms and sea ranches . . . they are always well paid, a ready market. And in peacetime there arc low taxes, no price and rent controls, no restriedon of profits, no scarcity of materials, no rationing, no priorities and regulations to contend with. Yes, the capitalist wants peace because peace pays. It pays for him!

“For him only! Not for the serviceman, the working man, the wives, mothers, sisters, sweethearts, the little children, the Postgraduate Citizens entering on an honorable retirement. They can be left to exist on a miserable unemployment compensation, or to fight for survival as prices soar. They can be left with idle hands. What does the Big Businessman, counting his swollen peacetime profits, care about them? What do the Interests care about you?

“I say to you, and I say it in all solemn truth: elect the Reactionaries and you get a peace. But elect the Liberals, our party—no, your party—elect the Liberals and you get a war. We have pledged ourselves before Almighty God to strive for everlasting world conflict.

If elected, I promise to go to Korea and stir up that war again; but this will only be the beginning.

“Are you going to stand in the breadlines because of these money-drunken Merchants of Life? Are you, once again, going to let British propaganda drag you into the European mess? Are you going to be gulled by the Peacemongers?”

The “NO!" that answered him was like thunder.

Royce turned the set off. There was a moment of silence.

“Well?” he said.

“Well, we have heard it before,” said von Thoraa of I. G. Farben, “What of it?”

“Discounting the emotional ranting,” said Royce, “it happens to be true. Now, doesn’t it?”

“For the capitalists, perhaps,” said Dmitrov, “Not for the Faithful. The so-called Orthodox Party wants war, of course, but not we of the Ref—”

“Yes, yes,” interrupted Royce. “It’s the same thing, though. Soviet and free world society have both become adjusted to war. So thoroughly adjusted that peace is a short-lived, abnormal, and disastrous thing. In the capitalist nations, like this one, peace means depression. In the Communist countries, peace means unrest. You can’t maintain good Communistic self-abnegation when automated peacetime factories are glutting everybody with more stuff than they can use.”

“That is how it works for the Orthodox,” said Dmitrov. “It offers empirical proof that their scienceless creed is mere idolatry. The Reformed Party, harking back to the Party Fathers, holds that the time for the state to begin withering away is now; and privately— we cannot admit it openly as yet— we agree that the state can only wither if war is abolished.”

“All right,” said Royce hastily. “Skip the sermons, please, Your Proleness. The fact is that these incessant, limited, non-atomic, deliberately inefficient little wars are all that keep the average man from smothering in his own productivity. As a result, the average man wants war, and you get symbols like the Kentucky Martyrs, and—”

“Kentucky Martyrs?” asked Krishnamura of India.

“Oh, they were a score of decorated soldiers who had to turn coal miner during the last peace. Down all day in a coal mine at twice the hazard, half the pay, and none of the rear-area compensations. The mine collapsed on them. The Liberals have played it up big ever since.”

Vallandringham looked desperate. “Please,” he said. “We are wasting time. At any moment, d’you realize, the Tory government may fall. And the Whigs are pledged to declare war on somebody.”

“I know,” said Royce. “I was just trying to get it across, the magnitude of the problem we face. And the rewards, if we can solve it.” He leaned forward, eagerly. “Let me tell you something. My outfit has found a uranium lode on Venus that makes the Belgian Congo look sick. There are billions of dollars in it if we could only plant a colony to mine the stuff. But can we do it with this stupid war going on?” He clenched hairy fists. “What do you think? We’re lucky to maintain a dozen spaceships of our own. Everything else has to be sold to the Lunar Fleet— at a stinking three percent profit!”

“Very well, very well,” said Castro. “We all agree. This has been the problem since we were in diapers, no? And now do you think you have a solution?"

“I’d damn well better have,” said Royce. “Business influence is waning every day, what with wartime taxes and Liberal sentiment. You all face corresponding situations at home. If we don’t act soon, it’ll be too late.”

“But do you, then, have an answer?” inquired Dmitrov. “An answer which will work for all countries under all forms of government?”

“I believe so,” said Royce. His lips tightened. “It’s going to seem pretty wild, but what have we to lose?”

They waited, with a gathering tautness. The city smoldered beyond the tower.

“Dr. Wald, if you please,” said Royce.

The little man stood up. He gulped and shuffled his feet. “My . . . my theory of . . . variable stars—” he began,

“Variable stars!” roared von Thoma. "Gott in Himmel, what have we to do tvith astronomers?” “Dr, Wald is a Nobel Prize winner,” said Royce dryly. “He was a pretty expensive astronomer.”

The scientist’s thin cheeks flushed. “Sir, if you are insinuating I accepted your . . . your bribe because—”

“Sorry,” said Royce. “Please continue.”

“I . . . well ... at Mr. Royce’s . . . uh . . . insistence. I . . . The theory of irregular variables is not at all well understood, you realize, and my . . . my word carries weight. Ah ... In three years of work, I have been able to, to produce a, ah, theory . . . account for fluctuations in luminosity and . . , and . . . fluctuations . . .” Wald looked miserable. So did his audience.

“Oh, never mind,” sighed Royce. “Sit down. I’ll put it in nickel words. The fact is that some stars expand every once in a while. There’s no predictability to it, they aren’t like ordinary variables. Nobody really knows why.”

“A nova,” said Vallandringham wisely.

“I wasn’t exactly thinking of a nova. Nothing on that scale. Just a small temporary upsurge of radiation.” Royce drew hard on his cigar and flickered his glance around the eyes that locked on him.

“Gentlemen,” he went on, "if it were authoritatively announced that in ten years the sun would increase its output enough to boil all the life off this planet—what would you do?”

Breath hissed out of lungs, explosively. “You don’t mean it’s going to?” whispered Krishnamura.

“Oh, no. Dr. Wald’s new theory only says it might. It’s a, shall we say, very plausible theory. Carefully tailored. Impeccable mathematics, and fits all the known facts. Nobody can disprove it. Neither can anyone prove it—unless the sun should start acting the way his theory says it would act about ten years before blowing up.”

“But will the sun be so obliging?" murmured Oliveira.

Buechley stepped forth. His face was sardonic. “That was my department,” he said. “I just got back from the neighborhood of the sun. Went within twenty million miles of it. Hot. We planted a bunch of missiles in orbit with super-H bombs for warheads. Each bomb big enough to rub a continent off the map. At a radio signal, those bombs are going to dive close to the sun, as close as the metal will stand, and explode.”

“But my God!” cried Vallandringham. “You might make a nova!”

“Oh, heavens, no,” said Wald. He was more confident of himself now when he could correct someone. “The masses and forces involved are, ah, mere firecrackers by comparison. You have no idea how big the sun really is. Why, all those bombs together, exploding simultaneously in the photosphere, could hardly raise one decent solar prominence. But exploding just outside, and releasing large clouds of energetic fluorescent gas—do you see? We can, er, fake some very spectacular prominences indeed. Exactly the type of prominence my theory predicts for a star due to expand in ten years.”

“We can do it again, from time to time,” added Buechley. “No strain.”

Royce grinned at the room. “If all the astronomers agreed that the world would end soon,” he asked somewhat rhetorically, “would you want to be bothered with fighting a war?”

“Gott, neinl” said von Thoma hoarsely,

“The panic,” objected Vallandringham. “The orgies . . .”

“Exactly,” laughed Royce. “For the first time in a century, there’s going to be a civilian consumption equal to the output of the factories. People will want to make the best of everything. They’ll have to work some, to earn the money to buy the luxuries, but I daresay a four-hour work week will be quite acceptable. Full employment, then— in peacetime!

“Of course, there’ll be some attempts to get a few people off Earth. The expanded sun would support life on the big Jovian moons. But first colonies would have to be planted, Earth-like atmospheres . . . and we have all the astronautical know-how! They'll buy all the space equipment we can sell, at our prices!”

“A ten-year orgy,” mused Castro. “Ten years of wild world peace . . .”

“And what, pray, happens when the sun fails to blow up?” demanded Vallandringham.

“Figure it out,” said Royce. “During the orgy, nobody will want to trouble his head over the drab business of politics. They’ll all be glad enough to turn the reins over to anyone who offers to take them. In a decade, Big Business, Reformed Marxism, the Federates, the Brahmins—all the interests we here represent—will be so firmly in the saddle no force could dislodge them. And during that time, the world will be so sodden we can maybe adjust all our societies to a form that can survive even a state of non-emergency.”

Von Thoma nodded in awe. “I like the scheme,” he said. “I think maybe even it works.” Then, slowly; “But I have an orderly mind. What about those establishments on Jupiter’s moons? Nobody will want them. What do we do with them after this is over?”

“Oh, that,” squeaked Wald. “I get that for my new observatory. Ten years from now, I had better be far, far away from Earth!”